Right, so.
So.
We keep going.
From where we we left.
On Monday, so uh.
Recap, we basically started talking about.
Uh, the non uh.
I'm sorry.
We were talking about um.
Asynchronous programming and in general
concurrency inside programming languages.
OK,
because concurrency in programming
languages is a introduces changes in a
way in which basically the semantics.
Our programming language had to leave the
beautiful mathematical world of functions,
of pure functions,
and had to land into the reality.
So communication error, of course.
But even if you are in the process,
concurrency and non determinism basically,
because at the end of the day the
operating system influence concurrency by
preempting threads etcetera. So please.
We introduce it in our programs some non
determinism.
2 different execution of the same program
can lead to different results,
which of course is a bad thing,
but fortunately we learned to use some
constructs such as monitors that we
discussed.
And synchronization mechanism that are
discussed in other in other courses so
that we can still preserve the essential
behaviour of a system,
even though if I look at the trace of
this execution of the of the program.
No programming execution are totally
equivalent to another programming
execution if you're going concurrent.
Big change with respect to a single
process program in which the execution.
Is entirely replicable all the time,
all the same given the same inputs.
But you know what?
We didn't discuss too much this.
We accepted some non determinism with
UI's.
OK, because in UI is the same,
you don't have well defined order or
timing in the action and so you start
reacting to the environment and produce
some behaviour and and basically the
macro behaviour application is consistent
in general.
When you press open,
a file diary will pop up,
but every time you will click on a
different pixel, different coordinates,
etcetera, etcetera. OK,
so at some point computers move it from
the pure mathematical.
Problem functional problem solving into a
world in which you have to deal with the
external world,
and this implies that not everything can
be anymore.
Purely abstract in semantics,
and in fact it's complicated.
There have been lots of attempt and there
are still attempts to make formal models
to describe the behaviour of concurrent
programs.
Or cloud applications or pick up the one
you want the most.
And so in the programming language
evolution, at some point someone said OK,
OK,
that we got libraries OK that my
programming language allows me to hook.
Into some external components that
provides me some abstraction,
but I'd like to have a consistent
semantics inside the language to deal
with these things,
and Java has been probably.
One of the first general programming
language,
so no specific for a specific application,
the a concurrent application,
but general purpose introducing threads,
sockets, network.
I mean before before Java in the in C
there are there is still no.
Network support.
I mean in CC has been defined without
network support.
Then you hook the socket library and
through the socket library you use the
the sockets and so you have network
implementation.
So it's very different than having a
system in case of the network is part of
the library,
but basically you have support for for
network for graphics.
And also graphics it.
And sooner.
I cannot see.
OK.
So that was basically the framework. OK,
so now today we start looking at.
Yesterday I started introducing.
An observation at the end of the class,
so let's start again from that point.
And I went back in time to the original
Ijax.
And I briefly commented that we it was
based on a component object,
binary component object,
component object model called COM.
But apart from this technical interesting
detail,
basically we we said OK to represent the
network in a single thread because that I
forgot to stress.
So if we go back in time, but still today,
JavaScript has no threads. OK,
I started with threads because threads
have been the first object that were made
available by the operating system and
they were the normal way to get
preemption inside your program. OK.
Because the cooperative programming
multi-threading can be implemented by
your own in C you can use set jump along
jump functions to do to implement your
own thread library, but that is.
Cooperative.
So there's no way to hook into an
interrupt that stops and etcetera.
You can use signals,
but I mean let me skip this and and so
basically threats were the obvious choice
because they were made available by the
operating system.
And the kernel was optimizing,
also optimizing the scheduling because
having multiple threads within the same
process.
Clearly the operating system tries to do
the context switch between threads of the
same process before jumping to another
process to reduce the context switch cost.
And so you've got some nice support in
the operating system.
And so that was seemed to be nice in
JavaScript.
This was impossible because in JavaScript,
JavaScript inside the web browser is a
single thread model execution. OK,
so the JavaScript interpreter is hosted
by.
The the web browser in this case and it
has just one thread. So there's no sleep,
there's no background,
there is no new start a new job.
So when and and that was one of the
reason because in the original model it
was impossible to.
To invoke an HTTP request from JavaScript
because JavaScript,
I mean network is by its definition
asynchronous.
I mean you open a connection and then you
wait for the answer and eventually you
will get the data. OK and so.
In a scripting engine designed to be
single threaded,
that was basically impossible. OK,
so the the component,
the XML HTTP request component introduced
what they introduced basically a state
machine.
With a programming pattern that is based
on the concept of event-driven
programming.
Have you studied even even programming
before? Yes. Oh.
Yes, OK.
I I didn't, you know, heard. Yes,
of course. So quick recap. Basically,
event-driven programming is a form of
execution of a program in which there is
a source of events.
These source of events,
which is often it started in graphical
programming because you don't know the
sequence of mouse and keyboard events.
Mouse and keyboards are shared between
multiple applications,
so there's no way to get hold of the.
Of the mouse in your application.
So basically every process has a queue.
The system takes control on keyboard and
mouse records,
decide what process should receive the
events and basically.
Post messages into a queue and so the
application has only to iterate on this
queue in a loop that is wait for event,
pick event, dispatch the event to the.
Event handler,
so the function that will do something
reacting to the event.
Of course there are default handlers so
that if you don't define your own handler,
the application will still behave,
otherwise will be a problem.
And and that's it.
So basically or now this callback
mechanism.
Is of paramount importance of course,
because basically you want to say when I
see a button click event in the queue,
I want to call a code that decides what
the button action should.
No.
And and this is beautifully implemented
in functional programming.
You associate a function value to the the
the the event handler and so whenever
there is the handler you invoke the
function because you use the functions as
high order as values so you can store.
Even array of functions and then then you
say for each element of array invoke the
the code back. OK,
so that that that is naturally
represented as a function.
But when graphics became popular system
where C were pointed to function were
used.
Or Java where interface were used or.
net which basically introduce delegates
to implement event viewing programming.
And as we said,
the difference between an interface and
and a delegate is that the delegate
represents a function with a given
signature as a type,
whereas the interface it's a stronger
binding in your because you have to
define a class which implements.
The interface. OK, but if I have,
I don't know,
a method that has two integers and an
integer,
I can cast into delegate with that
signature without any problem.
If I need to implement the interface,
then I need to have that particular
method, so I need to.
To create a wrapper.
So this is just a consideration and a
brief recap. OK, so.
End of the story.
The pressure because we started with
graphics then said OK network.
Oh also network we have to wait and and
why should I implement? I don't know.
In C you have the selector that allows
you to know if a file descriptor.
It's ready for data or not and so you can
pull multiple file descriptors to to to
to check whether there is data and then
read the data from the socket or a file
and and so basically but it's this is an
active weight.
In your program, but someone said,
come on,
can you just call me back when data is
available?
Why should I pull to check whether the
data is there?
OK and and so all the machinery that have
been developed originally for UI.
Has been borrowed and used also in
network also in.
Asynchronous programming. OK,
so and therefore event driven programming
has become a general pattern in which
basically you say.
There are sorts of events.
These sorts of events typically are
represented as objects in your system if
you are interested in doing something
upon some event happening.
I I simply.
Register a call back,
so either a function pointer,
an interface depending on the programming
language or a function or a Lambda pick
up whatever you want so that when that
happen event happens I.
We'll receive uh.
I will receive my method or my function
will be invoked. And you know what?
I forgot to mention one important thing.
Every event typically has a payload as a
bit of information. I mean,
you don't really care that the mouse has
been moved.
You also need the coordinates of the
mouse, OK?
And so typically in the typical
event-driven programming approach,
you you the function typically has has a
event,
whatever argument which contains details
about the event. OK,
so this is the general framework.
close the arenthesis.
Now on ready state change is a callback.
And this code back since JavaScript is a
functional programming language and so I
can pass a function as a value.
Then I assign to on ready state change.
The callback handler the semantics says
on ready state change is fired as event
anytime the connection changes state and.
In this case they use side effects,
so in fact they're not passing.
That would be much better.
The ready state as an argument to the
function I have to read.
The value from the connection,
but basically conceptually is the same.
OK and of course these works here. Why?
You see, now things are.
This works because.
What are we doing in this piece of code
from a functional programming? We are.
XHR 1 What is defined?
Here OK and we we are doing a a lexical
closure.
So this means that on ready state change
will be fired eventually.
You don't know when and clearly not in
this context.
So the the the lexical closure is a key
mechanism.
Because otherwise I wouldn't have the
ability to refer to XLXHR 1.
OK.
So this one is correct because it's
captured from the local variable and so
where whenever the functional value will
be invoked XHR one,
the language will ensure us.
That is the right one.
OK is this particular request. OK,
so we check the state.
There is some documentation that you go
and read and and find that state #4 is OK
and the status 200 is from HTTP.
And we all know that it's OK.
So if it's done and it's OK then.
I get the response text that is exposed
through the request and it is the content
of the HTTP request. OK,
so as you can see all the modern web.
That allows for single web page
application with incremental loading,
the list that keeps loading data from the
database, etcetera,
the the Facebook page which is 4 lines
and then keeps loading things has been
possible basically because this.
At some point has been added before this.
The only option for making web
application one reloading was reloading
the entire web page.
That was the only option.
And so basically these are performed
consequences,
but I don't want to explore them now.
Maybe we can use it as an exercise in the
upcoming days.
I'm planning to to have some exercise
because.
The exam is approaching and so we will
use.
We will take a number of use cases and we
will discuss together to to learn
something,
but at the same time to make some
exercise in in preview of the the the
exam.
Basically now part of the state of
applications lives inside the the DOM of
the web browser before this big change
before callbacks and Azure request.
The only option was to have the Dom in
fact stored on the web server.
Every time a page needed to be
regenerated,
you visit on the server side the Dom
generate the HTML.
And reproduce the page,
but unfortunately they were part of a
state that was impossible or almost
impossible to reproduce,
such as the scrolling level of a long
page, etcetera. So it was really quick.
So when these things happened,
it allowed to have much smooth user
experience interaction and it became.
Came quickly dominant to the point in
which entire frameworks were basically
dead because of this.
Microsoft Web Forms.
It was a strong enterprise framework used
by several enterprise to develop web
application,
which is still in use unfortunately in
this county.
Was basically dead.
Because it was designed to have the DOM
on the server side. And yes,
of course they added some trickiness to
be to be able to to this to do this thing
on the client side, but it never took off.
So eventually they redesigned everything.
Using React and modern technologies. OK,
but basically all these things were
possible because of this small piece of
code. Now we learned a lot of things.
First of all,
that the callback requires a state to
work.
And the state to work should be easy to
refer,
otherwise you will end up having a lot of
global variables in your program.
Because let's be honest,
without lexical closure,
I should have introduced either a global
variable or something else to store the.
Value of XHR one and this would have
clogged my code.
It would have been unreadable and very
difficult to understand,
but the fact that we have lexical closure
in our.
Pretty much.
I would say almost all programming
language by now or so empowered us.
In having the impression that all the
code is there,
all the state is local and so you are
full understand of what happens.
But nevertheless we don't have to forget
that this transfer the callback mechanism.
As some costs because these costs are
hidden and are in the fact that you are
referring to different threats or
concurrency.
Processes that are invoking our code in
different moments. OK, so look at this.
This if you remember I asked the to the
eye to generate an example with two
different invocation.
One after the other,
I need first to invoke a Service A and
then Service B right now.
Here, thanks to the lexical closure,
I described the full application in a
single place. I used a single state. Yeah,
I have the impression that everything is
in there, but.
From an execution perspective,
this is false.
I mean you invoke load data,
load data will allocate the XML HTTP
request.
It will set this function.
To the already state changed,
it will invoke open, send and terminates.
That's it. Execution done.
Then the send eventually will get the
data from the remote server and this
function will be invoked,
but this function will be invoked later
on when the activation of the load data
function.
Has already gone, is not anymore there.
And the same happens also for the
internal function.
So when this is invoked,
again this is executed and again a new
XML HTTP request is created.
And it will finish its execution
immediately.
Then the callback will invoke the event
handler,
which thanks fully to the lexical closure
mechanism.
Will still refer all the necessary state.
In this particular example,
only XH XH R2 is referred,
but in principle you can even refer also
to XH R1.
Because it's in the scope. OK,
so this is a beautiful example of several
things.
One thing that I I'm trying to draw your
attention,
and this is the reason because I'm trying
to go through.
All the dynamics is that statically from
the program text,
I've been able to describe my computation
as if it was a sequential program. Yes,
not exactly,
but I mean we can work and we learned
that with with the sugaring we can do a
lot of things, but basically.
We've been able to to tell OK first
already already state changed and then
second this and basically my actions are
one after the other as if it was executed
sequentially OK.
So this illusion is beautiful because it
allows us to have a comprehensive
understanding of the working of our
application without having to figure out
all the callback sequences.
Or which state is used?
OK.
And So what are the two main elements?
The 1st is.
Lambdas so that you can splice the
function code inside another function
code, etcetera.
And the second one is lexical closure,
the ability to capture and retain the
state so that even though the execution
of this code will terminate.
You still have access to the state of
that particular activation. OK,
I'm stressing it because it's very deeper.
It may be obvious, but it is not. In fact,
it took all of you sometimes to figure
out.
Lexical closure was the right name I was
looking for. OK.
Right, so.
And now you show an example of GPS style.
For the Ajax invocation. Oops,
let's see it. Different keyboard, OK.
O continuation assing style.
As you can see,
CPS in this context is clear and the eye
framing it even though I didn't.
So.
Code. Same code.
I I thank the actually she introduced
this the the the this tie in the context
without me having to redo another example
so.
First you have an Ajax get.
And the Ajax set as two arguments.
One is the URL,
which is the real argument. OK,
I want to fetch that URL and the second
argument is next when you've done.
Execute the computation will continue
invoke by invoking this next function OK.
So this is the essence of the
continuation passing style.
If you can't perform the full computation
for several reason in a single place,
then you say OK, I give you the arguments,
you do part of a job and then you pass on
to something someone else.
CPS can be used in many programming
pattern.
Sometimes you use it for the driver model
pattern. I mean it's not just concurrency.
If I have a different printer and I have
prepared document and print,
then you can say prepare document.
Then this is the function for printing
and the function will change.
Depending on the printer. OK, same side.
OK, basically you take the computation,
you split it in multiple steps.
Every step is defined by a function,
and then you compose them by using the
invocation.
To represent the scene, the the sequence.
Of course,
if you're doing pure mathematical,
I mean computations,
that's just function invocation.
But this style has the nice property to
be able to hide for the programmer.
Many complexities such as drivers,
such as callbacks, etcetera,
and give the programmer the impression
that he's programming an ordinary linear
function,
even though a lot of things happens
behind the scene.
OK.
Right,
so now and in how is implemented the code.
So you create the request,
you record the code back.
And then you simply invoke in the call
back next passing the text of the HTTP
request.
OK, that's basically the combiner.
This is OK.
Now my load data.
Uh.
Is not anymore creating explicitly all
the Ajax patterns, but basically say OK,
I want to do an Ajax get.
And this is the URL and this is what I
want to do.
When the Uh execution is completed.
And then I want to do another Ajax get
with another URL and this is the callback.
So now even though I have this extra
notation of Ajax set,
I have a piece of code that is.
Uh, get data.
Updated on get data updated on which in
my head are the two actions that I want
to perform,
so I'm able to hide under the hood all
the complexity that is.
OK.
Due to the fact that you are asynchronous.
OK,
so the continuation passing style has has
become basically.
An element of paramount importance
because is at the core the way these
things are implemented.
OK.
Notice there are no implicit returns.
From the callbacks because function
typically returns value.
In many continuation passing style,
it's complicated to obtain a type system
which is capable of dealing with any type,
because every function you will invoke
will have a different type.
Now if you are in a programming language
where we.
Uh.
With typing in the sense that you return
one of the base type and is dynamically
type checked etcetera, you don't care.
If it's statically typed,
it's complicated to model a general
purpose CPS style. So a typical.
Approach is EU side effects.
Which is not that great in functional
programming, but because.
Uh.
Typically you have the the function
invocation which triggers all the CPS
style invocations.
Then you can always say OK,
I do the closure and the last one will
return or as you do in the web.
You manipulate the DOM,
which is a global data structure that
everybody has access to,
and so you can have side effects.
That's another opportunity.
Or you can use monadic computations,
which is another way to hide. I mean,
me and Andrea,
we spent some time about monads. I mean.
Remembered monads were originally one of
the nice point.
It was to have a beautiful function on
the definition for representing the
console of the because the console has
stayed and so.
Through the monadic computation,
you can represent the console in a
functional,
consistent way without side effects.
So these are.
Considerations that depends on the
programming language, etc.
But at the heart of of the pattern,
the elements are these.
Basically you exploit this ability of
invoking function and capturing things to
be able to express logically a.
Single computation in in a single place
and use this this this computation.
Sorry the the the the ability to close
this state.
So that even though the computation ends,
you still have access to this state,
and so the impression is everything is
there.
Notice that this is from the semantic
standpoint. From the debugging standpoint,
it's complicated.
So if you set in your debugging
environment a break point and the
execution of the program stops and you
look for the thread ID,
it can easily happen that you have
multiple threads.
At every stop because you know know when
this happens and what this thread,
which thread will be the one executing
the handler.
OK.
And this is the reason because yesterday
Monday I was saying thread pool is still
there because someone has to implement
these things. OK.
And typically the core system libraries
when they have to provide a pullback,
they.
Resort to the thread pool for having a
thread waiting for some semaphore and
then as soon as the data is available,
notify by calling back. OK,
so that's the other part of the of the
world. So in the modern.
Current programming in language.
Of course you can still use explicitly
threads,
but we said that this is not so beautiful
because you have to synchronize and in
many cases you don't want to go parallel
that way.
Of course there are parallel algorithms
and in that case you must use parallelism.
OK,
but in many case in PROGRAMMING you you
don't want, you just want to say, OK,
I need to read the from the web.
It will take seconds,
which is eons in terms of a computer.
I want to just sleep and wait for the
data.
I don't want to stop my thread there
because threads are expensive.
I want to free the thread to go elsewhere
and and do whatever it needs to do and
whenever it's back I will continue.
Why do we need to be able?
I mean why if the thread is suspended?
One may argue why is that bad blocking a
thread? No, no,
I mean I'm blocking only that thread.
That thread is waiting.
So I mean I I just have.
No, that is in the queue of suspended.
Don't want to focus in a single thread
paradigm. No, that's correct.
But in a multi thread paradigm I can say
OK, who cares?
So why thread? I didn't ask this.
Probably I should have on Monday. I mean,
why do we need the thread pool? Why?
Can we create all the time threads or can
we block threads for every activity?
The point is that any system has,
especially the kernel of the operating
system, has a fixed number of everything.
It uses tables inside. OK,
so the number of threads is fixed.
When you stop a thread,
basically you are tapping the number of
activity that you can deal with
concurrently.
Imlications. Think of a web server.
The web. If I say one request, one thread,
if my system has 10 maximum 10
simultaneous thread,
I will be able to serve only 10 requests
at a time.
And for what?
For having the thread waiting for the
disk or for something other activities.
So it's a waste of resources.
And especially now,
remember when I was saying remember that
servers are expensive,
it's super expensive having.
You want an example?
Uh.
On Monday someone wrote to all of you
remembering that you have to activate the
multifactor authentication.
And you're so nice that every one of you
is replying back to me talking my e-mail
and.
So.
After 20 seconds, Sir.
From my OK ID Uni PET was and of course
lots of panicked students.
I have to do it, but I click it.
I'm not getting the web pages.
You're right honestly.
So you know what happened?
What happened that someone configured the.
DIT and EPIT with 10 workers. OK,
so and I mean.
It was designed to have 60,
000 people suddenly accessing the same
page and so the web server started
serving at most 10.
Request rest waiting connection timeout
is not working.
Solution 64 workers and now works
beautiful. OK, that's the impact.
So if you want to scale out,
so you want to be able that your system
is capable, sorry,
scale up to serve as much requests as
possible.
To be asynchronous allows you to wait for
resources without blocking threats.
That's the core and the reason because
the asynchronous PROGRAMMING has become
so popular is that a lot of resource
access network.
Disk database,
all the IO bound resources impose wait
and so with the synchronous PROGRAMMING
we we've been able to reduce
significantly the number of threads of
all the applications.
Without giving up on the number of
requests, you can serve at the same time.
OK and so when I write down a synchronous
function.
And when I wait and say that function,
it's it's not a trending isn't allocated
to read or that only that function will
be given to a trend and then I'll also
wait in this and that function.
Then they'll try to avoid.
I mean that if you await,
which is something we're about to to to
to see.
Basically you are telling the runtime
that you can,
as long as the semantics is that the
computation logically continues from that
point.
And the runtime and the compiler can do
whatever they want to obtain this goal.
OK.
You can give up the thread that is
executing. That's it.
I mean it's basically when like here when
you say.
Ajax get function response.
You say I don't care how it works,
how the Ajax get is implemented,
and I don't care if the thread that is
invoking this first is different than the
thread that is invoking the second part
as long as the semantics is.
Update, update.
So and and so my perception is that I get
the value, I set the value,
I get the value and I set the value.
I have a sequential view of my execution
even though.
Different threads are are involved. OK,
so at the end of the day you don't know.
And since you're using a thread pool,
it may by accident.
It may even be the same thread that keeps
going. You don't know.
Hmm.
Oh, by the way.
You can try to detect this and it's not a
good idea unless you don't know what
you're doing because there is a part of a
storage that is available typically
through operating system maybe I's to
access a particular storage.
Area which is called TLS Thread Local
Storage,
which is a place where you can store data
in the thread space. OK,
so if you use the TLS then you can
observe the the behaviour.
And This is why TLS in general is not
exposed in any of the scope of a
PROGRAMMING language for this reason.
Right.
Yes, please generate the the promise.
So naturally the AI understands what I'm
doing and it suggests me. Yes,
I mean you asked me to write the CPS pure
style, but you know in JavaScript.
There is a smarter way you can use
promises, OK.
OK.
O.
Promises are basically an encoding of
this style of PROGRAMMING into JavaScript.
It's a way to say OK.
You create an object which is the promise.
We do arguments. OK, the promise.
If it's resolved,
resolve will be involved.
If it's rejected, the promise.
They use promise because you promised to
do something. OK, it's counterintuitive.
I mean,
you would expect a wait or do something
as a promise.
I promised you that I will do something.
OK, so I promise the Ajax get of a URL.
Uh, returns a promise.
That uh, the URL will be fetched.
Now the problem is.
A voice to use,
I mean mix and match the language feature.
It's interesting because I mean it's not
a new feature in the JavaScript,
it's using in a smarter way the
JavaScript type system.
That we learn that that has no type
constructor,
everything is a dictionary or number or
string, etcetera.
So the promise being not a number or a
string is a dictionary and this
dictionary has been.
Preconfigured with some things,
for instance with the then.
Uh.
We did then method OK so and then I can.
Invokax Ajax get this returns me.
A promise object.
This promise object basically is
something that I can use to wait for the
promise. So Ajax get then invoke this,
then invoke that.
Catch in case of an error, do this.
No, no or both, because basically is.
There is the the reject.
So when you create the the promise,
the implementation of the promise says OK,
resolve is invoked when the promise is
satisfied.
Reject is invoked if in case of an error.
OK.
Yes, it is on both. You're right. I mean,
it is.
OK.
No, it's it's both the uh, so.
What happens? Uh.
See, this is interesting. Uh is the catch.
Uh, use it for.
OK, the answer is yes. OK,
but the the the question is legitimate
because I got this impression of a
sequential that we say OK,
but the catcher,
so it's only on the last and why not
catch and then then and then catching
again, OK.
Absolutely.
Oh yes,
I mean in the in the in the promise you
can do a lot of things, but I mean,
so it is a nice answer. OK,
I don't remember. I think it should work,
but.
The it will if the first fails basically
is still called the second promise and it
will fail again and then no that's that's
the question that I in my in my mind the
the things because you you you feel I am
hesitating is that.
The two actions, in fact,
are not really depending one after the
other.
Yes, no, no, yes. I mean yes,
because if if this then fail the second,
the the second one will not be invoked.
So the return will be a failure.
This will ignore the failure.
The catcher will deal with the app.
It's not. I mean, it's the attempt.
I mean,
if you look without thinking about the
dots.
It is something that you expect to read.
I mean try catch.
So clearly in when you read this thing is
this is the try body and this is the
single catch for all that is above.
So it's not, I mean.
It is the attempt to use all the
mechanism closures and objects,
etcetera to reproduce the appearance of a
sequential execution,
even though it is a chaos. OK,
so it makes sense, but this.
Sequence may lead to question uh for when
catch is uh uh invoked and notice that uh.
At least there is a bug in the in this
because it updates only so the.
When the second response two is involved,
because if the if the function response
one fail,
it goes straight to the hatch exactly.
But if the so if one is OK,
two will be executed because then says.
Basically say if it's, uh,
if it's resolved, go on. If it rejects,
stop.
OK, so this makes sense,
but basically if then response to fails.
Here at least we got a bug because uh,
we said we said the error only result one
and not in result two.
So at least there is a bug.
Oh, no, of course you're right. I mean,
of course when I'm saying is not,
it's not is the argument is not invoked.
But of course the function is executed,
otherwise the chain will be broken. OK,
but basically the then.
In the promise returns an object that
will inside the call back so that in case
of a success you can invoke,
in case of failure you can go on on the
chain.
So there is a hidden state that is passed
through all these things.
The problem of this pattern is because
you don't know which one it is.
Quite hard to know which one. Yeah,
in general in catch is normal.
In fact the in in in.
I mean not there is the error is argument,
but this is true for all exception
handling.
Well.
So in exception handling.
When you throw an exception,
you don't know where will be handled.
So the exception handling by its
definition,
you know that something happened and that
you have someone else that will.
Catch the exception will have the
responsibility to either fail or restore
some data integrity in my program. OK,
and you have no clue and in fact
exception and we didn't spend.
Much time in talking about exceptions
because it's annoying I will say,
but actually there is a lot of runtime
support for exception handling. A lot.
Because basically you alter the natural
flow.
So if I have a function that calls a
function that calls a function 10 times
and then in the.
The end an exception is raised. No one.
Until the first will deal with the catch,
you have to unwind the stack because
you're jumping from 10 nested function to
the top.
So exception handling by its nature is
not so deterministic.
OK.
One may argue. I mean,
I had such an argument with my PhD
supervisor, Professor Atadi,
which is now retired.
And he was saying that he was right that
exceptions by his definition should be
used only if the situation is exceptional
in the sense that the right if.
You develop a function which fails the
right, which is likely to fail.
The right way for implement is not
throwing an exception from that,
but returning a value which is error.
OK,
because the exception mechanism and and
go in this respect, I don't.
I'm not a fan of go,
I tell you and in go in this respect I
stride basically to say OK because people
abuse of exceptions.
I introduce the extra thing so that I fix
the people who use it,
but technically if I have.
Why exception are nice because in code
that open files it's not it's annoying to
try to write if open file if is equal
minus one then otherwise do that etcetera.
OK with the exception you throw.
Someone will take care.
I think it's a very interesting
discussion.
Anyone has a opinions about exceptions
because I mean exceptions are
uninteresting. So the exception exception.
By definition is an exception,
but even in the standard libraries are
used as a way to return an error to save
the cost and forcing to deal with the
exception.
Oh, I hate you.
You're bringing me on a different path.
So when Andrea covered the parametric
polymorphism, OK,
at some point if you remember C++
templates.
And by accident it was 99,
and by accident some programmer noticed
that it was possible to force the
compiler to execute code at compile time,
attempting to resolve.
Templates.
So basically template and a new form of
programming was coined that was known as
template metaprogramming,
which in C++ has been used quite a lot.
And then the problem was that all the
bugs were in the standard library.
Because the mark expansion expanded and
then and it was on the syntax uh ups and
syntax three of the code and then when
you type check the error was in the
expansion, so in the library.
And a lot of attempts that were made to
try to fix this,
but it never really has been fixed.
So exception are similar.
So exceptions are something that should
be exceptional.
So the code that was popular.
When Java made exception popular because
exception require runtime support because
you are breaking the normal flow of
execution.
So you have to unwin the stack and do
these things.
So when exception were made popular.
A lot of patterns we started using in
through exception,
through exception and try, catch, catch,
catch, exception and terminate.
Because the point is if you are close to
the exception source,
probably you know what's happening and
you can do something. If you try catch,
the only thing you can do is die.
And there is a lot of pragmatics about
how to and when to use exceptions,
but I think it's more pragmatics and
habits than the right way to do and
probably.
It's a compromise between returning
values that represents a consistent
return versus returning throwing an
exception someone will take in this
respect perhaps,
but this is an opinion never spend much
time.
Time in thinking about this thing.
So I mean,
it's an opinion that just by having a
conversation.
The the fact that you can you start in
this CPS inspired patterns,
you start seeing explicitly the failure
and the and the resolver.
It's a way to say OK.
Failure is part of the game.
Please don't throw an exception and by
return at least you know what can be
wrong. You're still in the same context,
you still have access to the to the to
the variables,
and so in this respect this is not an
exception.
Because you know exactly that one of
these in this chain has been wrong. So OK,
let's stop there.
Otherwise we take this discussion offline
because it is. I mean,
I know you have some counter-argument and
we probably probably produce some other
counter-argument.
But I think, but yes,
so for both failures.
Or only for the first.
Then.
Let's see.
Great question.
Handles any error in the entire promise,
which is what we knew.
Any error thrown inside so you get a
cache for free inside.
And of course unless you insert another
catch in the chain.
So basically you can say OK if I have a
multiple then I can say OK then then
catch because the next then I want it to
be performed.
Because basically the catch cancels all
subsequent steps.
So catch in this in this promise is
basically reset and restart.
So that's the reason because you can use
multiple catch in the in the pipeline.
Example oh,
we also get a visual flow and also.
Anywhere in the chain,
and as you were pointing out,
you don't know which one has failed.
Yeah, yes and no.
You can you can you can close it. Yeah,
you can close a variable and say and set
the variable in every function.
And so the last set is the last one.
Yeah, but.
Even the the best one is correct.
Unless you use TypeScript and you can do
some tricky things with the unit types
and it's a bit better. OK,
let's try to convert in a sync.
Await.
So promise basically use a variant of the
continuation passive style exploiting the
fact that you can insert into a
dictionary function.
So whenever you do dot,
basically you carry on more state
basically. OK, but it is a variant of.
passing style.
OK.
You have a nice syntactic sugar.
That is the await keyword that has been
become popular nowadays, which is.
Which basically say OK this function here.
Is a synchronous function and in fact is
a promise. OK, so being a synchronous,
I know that I can.
I will not get the result instantaneously,
so I'm going to violate the.
Return of the function. OK,
the the function will not reenter as soon
as possible because there is some
asynchronous workload somewhere. OK,
so and and this basically turns this
activity into a state machine at the end
of the day.
I'm done, error,
I'm working plus few other states. OK,
so at the end of the day,
when you turn some concurrent activity
into asynchronous,
basically you create naturally an object
which.
It represents the states of a computation.
Internally you have another object for
waiting and stuff like that,
and then the internal state to know in
which state you are. I'm still computing,
computation is done, error or result.
This is basically the list of interesting
stuff.
And so.
You want to say, OK,
can I wait for the result and and and and
the await then?
Suspend the thread or.
Release the thread to the thread pool and
records for a call back so that you can
get resume the computation as soon as the
waitable object is finished. OK,
clearly in this respect.
With respect to the then pattern,
this is more linear because basically you
have the standard.
Code. So you see.
You see?
How all these?
As evolved,
so now we introduce the annotation.
We say look,
load data sync is an asynchronous
function.
So be prepared.
This is not like any other functions. OK,
so if someone called this should be ready
to await the result because this function
will invoke a synchronous workload and
and this is clearly.
A chain first. Then you say OK,
I'm writing my code as if it was linear.
But then when I call the Ajax yet in this
case.
I'm gonna wait.
Its comutation then I will execute and
then I will await the second comutation
and then I'm going to execute.
In case of an error I will get a cache.
This will the sugar.
I mean,
this makes no sense in JavaScript
standard semantics.
Because basically.
This thing at the core is exactly the
same continuation passing style
JavaScript code,
because this will be the body of a
function that will be invoked upon the
completion. The completion, sorry.
And the same happens for this line and
this and and and the catch will be
because if someone throws a catch then if
the promise will get rejected then an
exception will be raised and then you
have to.
Catch the exception.
So this code gives you the illusion of
being a standard JavaScript function,
but actually it alters completely the
semantics of the language.
The nice thing is that it is super
optimizing the CPU and other system usage
because it's not upon you, the programmer,
to decide whether that should be a thread,
another thread if I have to schedule.
A task waiting for the task,
having a mailbox pattern to store all the
results that are coming.
I mean I'm writing and I say OK,
I can wait as and then the compiler or
the runtime will take care of turning
this into.
Continuation passing style invocations.
The price to pay debugging,
the debugging should be very good and
during the debugging you may notice that
all this complexity pops up.
On the good and on the pro side.
Uh, it is uh uh.
The state management is self-defined.
I mean,
even though you are calling in different
moments, different functions, etcetera,
you have a comprehensive view of the
state of the computation and you have
full control what's happening.
And the runtime will turn these into
standard patterns that everybody should
understand. OK, so.
Can you show me a similar example in C?
No. So the first one was F#.
F# using active workflows introduced the
the asynchronous monitor.
And and because F team was in Microsoft
and still is now is an open foundation,
but basically Microsoft is back in back
in the foundation.
Of course all many of the successful
patterns from F sharp were borrowed in C#.
I'm using C# because I know that you're
more familiar with the Java like syntax
than the F syntax.
So it's interesting to see what's
happening in C# because C# forces us to
see the types,
which in JavaScript I don't have,
but looking at types let us understand
better what's going on under the hood.
So.
HTTP which is the HTTP client gets string
async.
This is a program that that's pragmatic.
So this is a programming pattern in C#.
I mean it's not mandatory, but it's a.
A good thing to do using the sync suffix
to the methods that are asynchronous so
that you can you know that that's
considered to be asynchronous.
So get string asynchronous you get you
give the URL.
And then you do await,
you write O exactly the same.
OK.
Manual wraers. OK, let's use this.
OK.
So I think I I I wasn't thinking about
this, but basically it is what I was.
So in C# you can have.
Asynchronous methods.
So if I said a sync, get a sync,
a sync keyword,
then the return type will be a string.
If you don't say that get async is
asynchronous,
then the return type is a task of string.
So as you see,
basically asynchronous functions are
monads that go into the space of task of
T.
So an asynchronous function gives me back
a task which represents the asynchronous
computation of some type of which is the
return type of the function.
So get async is a function which returns
a task.
And when I invoke get string async,
I will get the task which returns a
string.
Can you show me now an example of C# use
of seeing await?
And the the sugared form.
Use a different example.
OK,
so otherwise he would keep writing me
back an example with the two things.
So in the async await.
You have.
OK.
So the main in this example,
the main is asynchronous.
I didn't even know that you can do that.
OK, you learn simply always something.
And of course since the signature of main
method is void,
then the return type is task,
not task of T because there is no return
value. OK, good to know.
Then you say OK, I want to read file sync,
so I invoke this method and this method
we know that returns.
A task of a string,
so a task or computation will result into
a string.
And here you're calling,
you're saying await.
So when you do await on a task,
basically the code generated will wait.
For the task to complete,
take the result and return the result.
So text will be the string result of the
task of the synchronous task.
And of course,
method async as read file async is an
asynchronous method because he waits for
the async version of the riddle text in
the file.
So that the content this is the content.
And notice that there is this syntax is
tricky.
Because the content of which type is.
Sorry, straight. Oh, straight.
O you are returning a string in a method
that is declare task of string.
And this is acceptable only because that
method is asynchronous.
And so they the authors of the language
prefer to keep.
Task to stress that the the real return
is not a string,
is a task which returns a string in even
though they de sugar this thing into
something. OK, so in to what?
This thing the sugars look at how much
code is generated on your behalf.
OK.
So.
You say OK.
You create a a state machine.
You said the state of a number you don't
care. It's the compiler.
Basically -1 is before the end.
Then you start and you and you you pass
the the the reference to the state
machine so that you can have side effect
and update the state and everything.
And at the end, uh,
you you return the task.
And the main state machine implements the
interface, which is basically move next,
which is perform another step in the
computation and and and and is on any
state machine there is a typically switch.
State next step standard implementation
of our finite state machine.
And.
Here you read the file, you get a task.
And.
The awaiter is an internal object which
is the the object that allows you to
suspend and restart because I mean
someone has to do the work of releasing
the thread.
OK.
So if it's not you, it's the library.
OK. And then there is a.
Can you tell me more and show an example
of task of T?
User.
Now it is not just OK, what is the task?
What can I do with the task?
The typical thing that you can do in with
the task is wait.
So the task has a wait method which
basically is the same as doing a wait
using the syntactic sugar.
Because the state machine, I mean that is.
Thank you. Ah
The state machine is the most efficient
imlementation.
Of that pattern and it it is the less
readable. So if you are a human,
you prefer the promise like then etcetera.
OK,
but that will cost you a lot of frames on
the stack.
The state machine requires only one
integer and that's it.
And the code is totally unreadable as
we've seen.
But that is compiler generated.
You don't care.
There is a mapping from few lines to the
board code that is generated,
but that is the most efficient way you
can implement the final state machine.
No.
I mean you you typically do wait.
You can do wait.
Because I mean the then as the problem.
I mean JavaScript gives no don't give
enough control to use.
JavaScript has a lot of limitation inside
the browser.
No one want to call to touch the core
JavaScript core.
So basically then syntax hides a lot more
because there are some operation that it
it's like sleep.
Sleeping JavaScript is complicated. OK,
because JavaScript JavaScript has a
semantics that is basically single thread.
In.net or Java, I mean I'm showing.
net but it applies to many other
languages.
You don't have this restriction,
so you can basically say task dot wait
and you know that the next line will be
executed after the task finish and so
then.
It's useless.
It will just complicated things.
You see, you can delay.
Or you can wait.
You can create a task manually.
Then you can consume.
And then you can check whether if it's
faulted or not.
OK.
Now can you show the relation between
tasks and threads?
That's the.
Those tasks.
Represents the computation.
Threads represents the execution of the
computation.
O the thread you can say do work,
start and you do the thread.
In the task you can say run.
OK.
The task run goes to the thread OOL,
which uses a thread.
So now after four hours you have
basically a big picture in which you see
all the relation between these things
that may seems different,
but they are all part of the same
architecture.
So threads are the core implementation
coming from the operating system and this.
These are operating system tasks because
of preemption.
It would be difficult to implement
preemption in the programming language.
OK, so you map threads into the language.
First step Java 9596.
Then you say oh,
but I can't allocate a new thread every
time because the number of threads is
finite and so I will block how much my
program can scale up in terms of the
input.
Solution.
Thread pool.
I allocate a bunch of threads and I
introduce a queue. Some will wait.
But this works because these are small
activities. So you know that it's take,
execute, release, take, release, take,
release.
So the queue will not wait long and if
the queue grows too much,
I can still allocate a new thread,
not a bunch of threads so that.
Uh, more job. I wanna use the latency.
I allocate some more resource. OK,
let's do that.
Then you say task.
Task is an abstraction which represents
an asynchronous computation which is
represented at the end of the day as a
fine state machine.
Then you can start using syntax by using
the continuation passing style and hide
all the state machine etcetera,
exploiting the fact that the function can
be involved and you got lexical closures.
And on top of that you the sugar or you
sugar, you the sugar when you go down,
you sugar when you go up,
you sugar with the syntax.
So you give the impression to write a
single function which at the end of the
day use all this chain.
OK, so this ends to some extent.
I think I could have said a lot more,
but maybe in the future.
But this is the minimum journey we can go
into the asynchronous world.
So the asynchronous programming is a form
of parallel programming.
But it's a very specific form.
It is mostly effective for the IO bound
computations, net and files,
so not a big part, a small part,
or also machine internal machine.
IO bound computation GPUs.
When you use an LLM, OK,
you're in a similar part in the control
program,
which I mean you load the model into the
GPU then.
You ask the the net to do something,
etcetera. This happens in the GPU.
You in the CPU that you want just to send
back the tokens, etcetera.
You're waiting the GPU.
So I think it's good, OK.
3.
In fact,
the stream are the typical representation
of the output of an LM,
which is related to the async because I
mean the stream.
If you look at the implementation,
the graphical implementation in in web,
you see the text appearing etcetera.
Those are events,
so they use typically web events to send
back fragments.
You receive the event and you open the
text in the in the in the web UI.
OK and all this is because naturally is a
sequence of token generated.
Which is similar to a file that is red,
and so it's naturally modeled as an
asynchronous computation because every
token it may takes a while to produce it
and so OK, but this is just to tell you.
Several application are there.
This has become a founding pattern,
so one last example.
Now,
can you show me an example of a sync in
F#? Now I did promise you this,
but I won't dig down into the details,
but if you will, please,
this is a good exercise.
Eyes to understand by asking the AI the
implementation of async in F sharp.
And how this relates to the monads and
the bind and everything.
OK.
I don't think, uh, OK,
it's still generating, right? Perfect.
OK,
so as you can see now you're using the
active workflow.
So from F sharp the async monad is
analogous to the sequence because it is
rewritten in bind.
The bind is a form of continuation for
system.
Oops,
monads are implemented in continuation
passing time and.
Uh.
And and then in this case you don't even
you use the lead bang that is rewritten
the sugar the in the monadic form in one
of the methods that define the the
monadic object and this is equivalent to
a weight.
In the other here you also have the
forward pipe,
so you say OK get a sync a await task.
So in this case you await and then and
then return the content which is an
asynchronous value and.
Is a task bot, etcetera.
So that's another definition.
But as you can,
as you've seen that async has become in
the last 10 year has have been
implemented in most of PROGRAMMING
language because are very useful part
general PowerPoint patterns.
Which joins functions, et cetera,
and made the program programs more
readable with respect to the counterpart
without this sugaring.
But we also learned that at the end of
the day is a big sugaring sugar coat that
you you put on top of these objects that
have been.
Exposed it inside the PROGRAMMING
language semantics during the 90s.
I hope that I enlighten you at least a
little bit and I thank you again and I
see you tomorrow, 2:00 PM.